<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Planet]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[One planet!]]></description>
        <link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2016 06:10:42 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mapping Kindergartens While Doing My Fieldwork Using Maps.me]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>This is the first diary entry I make on openstreetmap.</p>

            
            <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/user/asdofindia/diary/39052">Read the linked post</a>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">http://asd.learnlearn.in/osm-mapping-while-working-maps-me/</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Akshay S Dinesh]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2016 22:28:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Haridwar]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[This notorious place. Do anything you want, but never eat a thing from  here. They are probably taking all their water from the E-coli filled  dirty sacred holy river Ganga. We had no plan to eat at the bank of the  river, but it rained and we got trapped near a place and we ate some and  the story turns worse.<br />But before that, we had some nice  time walking by the side of the river. We had reached the Haridwar  railway station by afternoon. And the Russian would leave for Delhi in  the 18:15 Shatabdi Express. He was particular that he goes in an air  conditioned train because of what had happened on our journey from Delhi  to Dehradun. All of us had something to cover ourselves with, except  him. We were in sleeper compartment. He went to his berth like a Russian  and we assumed Russians were resistant to cold. Turns out they aren't.  They just have excellent warming systems in their place. So, the outside  temperatures might go below zero, but inside the homes are warm. And in  the morning all of us had woken up from a good night's sleep except  him. So he couldn't miss this AC train to Delhi.<br /><br />But we  still had some time to pass before the train would arrive. There were  so many police officers deployed in the railway station. Turns out it  was indeed a special occasion and we would have cursed ourselves if we  had reached there a day later. It was going to be an 'ardh kumbh mela'  next day. Means a lot of devotees running to the river. Anyhow, we  walked perpendicularly towards the river.<br /><br />The banks  were surprisingly calm. There were a few devotee groups sitting here and  there. People dressed like Lord Shiva kept walking by us. The river was  mighty, filled to the brim. We walked more than a kilometer like that  and took enough photos on the way. After all, the river is a river.<br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-gOIE0mwyHhs/V33x3e1tRdI/AAAAAAAAMCI/-jkPLB1X4h8kWeqNhmQk0lXcwzwexbTcwCLcB/s1600/ganga.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="43" src="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-gOIE0mwyHhs/V33x3e1tRdI/AAAAAAAAMCI/-jkPLB1X4h8kWeqNhmQk0lXcwzwexbTcwCLcB/s320/ganga.jpg" width="320" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;">Panorama</td></tr></tbody></table><br />We  were walking towards a huge Shiva statue. But it was too far for us to  walk to and it appeared to be on an island all by itself. Instead we  decided to go to this part of the river where they would float lamps on.  We were there, but it wasn't time yet for the devotees to come in  masses with the lamps. So we decided to check out the shops on the  parallel road. This is where it rained and we got charmed into eating  thalis and kesari from a dhaba.<br /><br />When the rain  subsided, it was time for the Russian to leave. We dropped him back at  the station waving him goodbye. On the way to the station we had nice  warm tea at another shop too. And then we came back to the place where  the lamps would float.<br /><br />The lamps had started floating.  There was a small mandir on the bank where people would fetch these  from. There also was a monkey on its roof trying to steal the bananas  offered to the God there being rattled away by the priest. Then there  was this set of people standing in the river with water up till their  knees. They would use a piece of glass (or transparent plastic?) to look  through the surface of the river on to the bottom and pick something  from the bottom using their long magnetic stick. Turns out, coins. Look,  pick, transfer. Repeat.<br /><br />We observed them and the floating  lamps for a while and then walked around the city. There was a Chinese corner where we had noodles and soup. Night had fallen and that would be our dinner. We then walked to the riverbank again. There were cold seats to sit on. We sat with the breeze hitting us hard and the mighty river tempting me to jump into and die.<br /><br />After a while, we went back to the railway station. They had a  waiting room upstairs. Filled with people though. We spread a newspaper  and sat outside. Our train was coming only after midnight. I slowly drifted into sleep. <br /><br />]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-668652011781121325.post-1813149938146782040</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Akshay S Dinesh]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 06:43:22 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mussoorie]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[We reached Mussoorie around 4 o'clock. Although we saw the youth hostel  on the way we weren't sure if they provided accommodation and it was a  bit far from all the places we wanted to trek to. At the bus stand an  agent approached us asking if we wanted rooms and then led us to a  nearby hotel where we got a large room where the 4 of us could stay. The  Russian asked if a room warmer was available. It was, at ₹200 extra. We  went for it and that decision was a lifesaver as you will soon come to  know.<br /><br />By then the Sun was going to go down and we didn't  want to waste that day by not going anywhere. I calculated the distance  to various places we could go to and settled on going to Everest house.  The distance could be covered on foot in about an hour said Google Maps.  But that hour easily stretched into two. I'll write about how  GPS-enabled/dependent our treks were in a later post.<br /><br />We  did get lost once and reached a high-security hotel with dogs that  would look like they could rip you apart. But we retraced, walked, and  stomped our way forward. At about 800m to Sir George Everest House you  reach this cafe called Seagreen. It was really dark by then and so we  decided to go to the Everest House first and then go to the cafe on  return even though we were really hungry and hadn't had any food (I had  promised my travel mates that there were so many restaurants on the way  where we could eat from, but turns out the map is different from  reality). Here, two dogs joined us on the upward climb.<br /><br />The  climb is steep but there is a clear unpaved path upwards and although  it was dark we had enough moonlight to see our way. The dogs - we named  them Schwanan (Malayalam for dog) and Hillary. We were so late that the  tiny shops on the sides which would sell soft drinks and noodles were  closing down one by one. It was still wonderful how there were people  running such shops everywhere. Schwanan was leading the way at times and  at other times slowing down to catch up with Hillary who was trailing.  But I realized that day that these were probably the descendants of  those very same dogs which gave Sir George Everest company when he  climbed that hill to set up his house on top.<br /><br />And then  we reached the house, quite literally at the top of the hill and at the  edge of the land. But to call it a house would be a mistake because all  that remained were a few walls which have now been written over with  names of couples inside huge ❤ symbols.<br /><br />And then there  was a surprise. There was light! There were the Himalayan mountains far  away glistening in red, orange, and all the colours of the setting Sun.  The horizon was a rainbow between the starlit dark sky and the snowy  white mountains. We were the only people there, the last trekkers of the  day. The 4 of us and Schwanan. Hillary had gone away somewhere else.<br /><br />We  spent only about 15 minutes on the top because we were hungry, it was  getting cold, it was getting darker, and we had taken enough panoramas  and selfies and timer shots. On the way back, we had to intermittently  shine a fridge market torch one of us had to make sure there were no  snakes or holes. And we did stop here and there to look at the stars and  make out random constellations that didn't even exist.<br /><br />As  we had decided we took a break at Seagreen Cafe where we had a large  pizza and hot coffee. More importantly they had a room warmer which  worked on coal maybe and we took a lot of warmth from it. Working on his  tablet was a fellow traveller who was spending some time in North India  before flying to Scotland to meet his girlfriend. We waved him goodbye  and walked back, trying and failing to hitchhike. On the long way back  which felt shorter, the 3 of us who were Malayalis sang some of our boat  racing songs to keep us going faster. When we got tired, the Russian  taught us his marching songs too. We reached our rooms and slept  peacefully with the warmer first on, and then off.<br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-Yu75UxaHcm8/V33rKoElN-I/AAAAAAAAMA4/sh_4UEnCvGszQzAFrCks9l7xDtGHfFZ3ACLcB/s1600/warmer.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="320" src="https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-Yu75UxaHcm8/V33rKoElN-I/AAAAAAAAMA4/sh_4UEnCvGszQzAFrCks9l7xDtGHfFZ3ACLcB/s320/warmer.jpg" width="237" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;">This is where warmth comes from</td></tr></tbody></table>For  next day, I had decided that we would trek to a "Tibetan Buddhist  Temple" which looked good in photos on Google Maps. We woke up early,  had breakfast and started walking. We weren't even a kilometer down when  it started to drizzle slightly. We walked on till the rain got heavier  and we had to find shelter in a building on the roadside. As we stood  there we tried to find a hike to the temple but unfortunately it was too  early in the morning and there were no vehicles going that side. The  rain gave in slightly and we continued to walk. checking off landmarks  to make sure we were on the right path. But then, all of a sudden there  was heavy downpour and our woollen clothes were absorbing all the water  like a camel at an oasis. We tried taking cover again, but by then we  were so wet and so close to the temple on the map that we decided to  brave the rain.<br /><br />There was ice on the road. It was a  hailstorm. There was water everywhere. Our shoes were wet despite our  best attempts to not step on water. And the hail was hitting us hard  too. Anyhow we reached the Buddhist temple. Like the rain wasn't enough,  the temple was closed that morning. We could not go inside, but we  could take photos from outside and see the valley. As I was trying to  take a picture of the temple, I realized to my horror that my fingers  were getting so cold that I could not bend them to click. It was the  case with everyone. We were going to die probably while still searching  for an open cafe to buy some warmth.<br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-m5QQXU7ejAI/V33qsUTAWpI/AAAAAAAAMA0/d1U2J7acBzQAeEqkUilV64VYs0mj2ZIoQCLcB/s1600/photo851520839331457166.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="320" src="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-m5QQXU7ejAI/V33qsUTAWpI/AAAAAAAAMA0/d1U2J7acBzQAeEqkUilV64VYs0mj2ZIoQCLcB/s320/photo851520839331457166.jpg" width="237" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;">This was everywhere!</td></tr></tbody></table>But there was a  saviour. The language teacher of a Tibetan school there was going to  Chandigarh in his car. And after removing all the hailstones from his  car's windshield he was willing to drop us back to the city. We jumped  in and he turned the AC on to full heat, dropped us near our hotel, and  we ran to our rooms after thanking him and wishing him a happy journey.  When we reached room we were drenched and shivering. The only warm thing  in the room was the warmer and we sat around it warming our clothes and  body in turns. The wet socks were fuming. Shoes definitely had to be  dried. The room service brought cups of tea and we had bought some  bananas on the way. After about an hour we were dry enough to pack up  and leave.<br /><br />We had brunch at a nice warm restaurant just  above the bus stand. It was still raining. The Mussoorie Library were  Ruskin Bond is known to frequent was right next to us but we were in no  mood for reading. The buses to Dehradun are the same buses that come  from <a href="http://blog.learnlearn.in/2016/07/dehradun.html">Dehradun</a>. We waited for about half an hour and got our seats back  to Dehradun.<br /><br />As soon as we reached the bus stand I  realized there was a train about to leave from the station - the  Dehradun Allahabad Link Express. We ran to the station and made sure the  train hadn't left and then ran to the ticket counter which is outside  the platform and took tickets and ran back to the train and got in to  the general compartment and the train started, all within a span of ten  minutes. The compartment was full and the Russian got the taste of  general compartment journey and we alighted at <a href="http://blog.learnlearn.in/2016/07/haridwar.html">Haridwar</a>.<br /><h3></h3>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-668652011781121325.post-4566291266661966642</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Akshay S Dinesh]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 06:55:50 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Dehradun]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[The <a href="http://blog.learnlearn.in/2016/03/delhi-my-city.html">Delhi</a> Dehradun express stops for long time at various places and  reaches Dehradun by 9 in the morning. We woke up by the time the train  reached Haridwar and saw dried Ganga on the way.<br /><h3></h3>At Dehradun railway station, you can walk outside to the  Dehradun bus stand where there are half hourly buses to Mussoorie from 6  in the morning to 9 in the night. We walked further, had breakfast, and  walked through the market to reach clock tower. From the clock tower a  small bus took us to Forest Research Institute at ₹10.<br /><br />There  were a couple of other tourists waiting in the electric cart at the  entrance. We quickly bought entry tickets and sat on it. I was at the  tail, looking back when the cart went forward. The straight road cut at  right angles to several buildings, all in lush green plots.<br /><br />The  cart dropped us at one end of a large, imperial building built of red  bricks. This was the Forest Research Institute. Some of the corridors  reminded us of Hogwarts.<br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-EJI_eOEudLY/V33wtpsZigI/AAAAAAAAMB4/-Sf4Y02HXc4W6whGGk7-Cjt3_M0_Ui_ugCLcB/s1600/afri%2Bhogwarts.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="320" src="https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-EJI_eOEudLY/V33wtpsZigI/AAAAAAAAMB4/-Sf4Y02HXc4W6whGGk7-Cjt3_M0_Ui_ugCLcB/s320/afri%2Bhogwarts.jpg" width="237" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;">See?</td></tr></tbody></table><br />There were multiple  "exhibitions" inside the building. The entry ticket would cover all of  them. But the exhibitions were rather the various departments of the  Forest Research Institute. For example, there was this pathology  exhibition, in which the pathophysiology of all the plant diseases were  shown (with pathological specimens just like our medical college).  Siviculture exhibition was about cultivating forests and there were tiny  models of forests showing how the trees looked at different height. In  another room, there were cross sections of 800 year old trees showing  tree rings that corresponded to different years in the history. One of  these rooms, I heard about <i>cordyceps sinensis</i> which is a fungus  that parasitically grows out of worms apparently more expensive than  gold and extremely difficult to procure. <br /><br />A nearby  school had come for picnic there and when we got outside the Institute's  garden was full of kids playing different games in their own little  groups. This is also where our Russian friend saw someone posing in one  of the classic Bollywood hero poses and imitated those himself. We  started walking back and got on to the electric cart about a minute down  the path. Then we took a vehicle back to the Dehradun city back to  where we started from.<br /><br />At the bus stand, there were  regular and frequent buses to <a href="http://blog.learnlearn.in/2016/07/mussoorie.html">Mussoorie</a>. All we had to do was stand in  queue and reserve seats in the next bus that was going up. The ride is  just under a couple of hours but the road is winding and uphill.]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-668652011781121325.post-1890679606526285323</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Akshay S Dinesh]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 06:04:06 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why decentralize technology?]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>Decentralization is the process of ensuring no ownership or control is limited to a single entity. The issue of decentralization is important in politics, economics and technology to limit the amount of impact a single, centralized body can have over the ecosystem.</p>

<p>In politics, we see this in the form of federal governments, where control of execution is handled down to the lowest governance levels. This distributes the responsibility and decision rights from autocratic or pseudo-democratic agents to the citizens. Important tasks are divided and spread across roles and regions to avoid single point of failure or corruption, in case those in authoritative position fail to do their tasks. This may not have worked out ideally so far across the world, but this gives maximum choice to citizens to express their concerns and take action.</p>

<p>In economics, the concept of decentralization is broad, but it boils down to efforts for overall economic prosperity by ensuring that no single entity controls the flow of money, distributing economic policy control and distributing flow and creation of currency.</p>

<p>In technology, this means creating a system with no centralized control. Decentralization in technology can promote open access to information, provide improved <a href="/privacy-in-technology.html">privacy</a> and create more resilient systems.</p>

<p>The internet is our backbone today for creating decentralized systems. Internally, it is built through multiple layers of technology — at the lowest level we have hardware cables that relay signals across the globe, then we have protocols that convert these signals to data packets that our computers can understand, then we have software that we use to create, serve and consume those data, like web servers and web browsers. At its core, the internet as technology embodies all the principles that builds successful decentralized systems.</p>

<p>The “World Wide Web”, the one that we fondly call “the web”, is built on top of this internet by utilizing servers that serve data, a globally distributed domain name system (DNS) that translates names to IP addresses and web browsers that can convert the data received from those servers and render them into interfaces for human interaction. The power of the web comes from the ability to <em>link</em> to other web resources that do not reside on the same server, thus creating a globally traversable pool of information. So, all the information in the world does not need to remain on one huge mega-computer. It can be decentralized; spread out across millions of computer across the globe that form part of the network and exchange information with each other.</p>

<h2 id="regression-to-centralization">Regression to centralization</h2>

<p>The technology stack of the internet actually consists of multiple eventually-centralized processes.</p>

<p>Like, the DNS works by having a record of domain names that map to IP addresses. We can host our own DNS servers, but on public networks and the internet we use daily, we are dependent on centralized name servers that are called “root name servers”. DNS queries follow a chain of name resolution up to the root name servers and try to resolve a domain name to its IP address. Even though this removes the requirement of every computer having to remember every other computers’ IP, the root name servers still form a centralized part of the domain name resolution service.</p>

<p>Also, as we take our internet subscriptions from internet service providers (ISPs), all of our internet traffic passes through their hardware through to the undersea cables. This means, if a government or any agency for that matter can control the ISPs or damage the undersea cables, they can take down the internet. We see these happening in the form of governments asking ISPs to restrict access to certain websites or by trying to censor the internet usage of the entire country or by banning internet completely.</p>

<p>The trouble does not end there. If we move one level higher, we see the internet traffic today is becoming increasingly homogeneous. Five or six corporations account for the majority of internet traffic today. This has happened over the years by creating services which users of the internet have learned to depend on, be it their emails or documents or videos or chatting with friends. The truth is, these corporations do offer services of significant value. But, at the same time, they subvert the decentralized nature of the internet by either amassing user data thereby establishing eventual dependency or by <a href="https://googleblog.blogspot.in/2015/09/bringing-the-internet-to-more-indians.html">trying to be the gateway to the internet</a> or, worse, by <a href="http://qz.com/333313/milliions-of-facebook-users-have-no-idea-theyre-using-the-internet/">pretending to be the internet</a> itself.</p>

<p>And then, we have the “cloud”. Cutting across the various (mis)interpretations, a “cloud” is simply another computer always connected to the internet where you can store your data or offload your computations. The cloud has proven to be an effective measure to silo users and create centralized services where an entity can control what happens with the data. Once again, it is not about whether this is “good” or “evil”. It is about whether it is a resilient solution that pays off in the long term. Once a data is in a cloud, it is dependent on the resiliency of the systems in the cloud to ensure no data leaks happen or no data is corrupted. Even if we assume that such a cloud is safe enough, we run the risk of the cloud system wiping our data and terminating our account or leaking out data to surveillance agents under pressure from governments. In short, it is not a good enough solution, yet it has met with huge success.</p>

<p>It seems that in the process of making successful businesses around the internet, we have made a regression to centralization and almost removed the idea of an open playground.</p>

<h2 id="bringing-back-decentralization-of-the-internet">Bringing back decentralization of the internet</h2>

<p>There has been multiple commendable efforts to promote decentralization of the internet. There are two major obstacles, however:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Technological</em> - It takes a lot of research and efforts to build such systems. I’m talking about decades worth of effort.</li>
  <li><em>Awareness</em> - People have become too comfortable with having one account that gives them all facilities from emails to document storage to chat. It is hard to ask people to change, unless you have a better deal.</li>
</ul>

<p>This is why the people behind <a href="http://maidsafe.net">MaidSafe</a> have been researching for over nine years to create a better version of the internet, one that is decentralized, secure and privacy-aware. Then, there are the minds behind <a href="https://matrix.org">Matrix</a> who have been working on creating a standard for secure, decentralized communication. There are joint group efforts like <a href="http://redecentralize.org/">Redecentralize</a> who, as part of advocating for a decentralized internet, maintain a directory of <a href="https://redecentralize.github.io/alternative-internet/">projects working on decentralization</a>. There are crypto-currencies like <a href="https://bitcoin.org/">Bitcoin</a>, <a href="http://maidsafe.net/safecoin.html">Safecoin</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_cryptocurrencies">others</a>. This is not an exhaustive list, but an indication that the technological challenge has not scared people away. Those who believe in that idea, have eventually come forward and taken up the hard work. These are the people who in turn motivate my work on projects like <a href="https://github.com/muktakosh/unicorn">unicorn</a>.</p>

<p>We may be close in achieving the technological goals, yet the awareness part is still a big problem. We need to focus on building an ecosystem of technologies that talk to each other without as much centralization as possible. From a user’s perspective, those things need to <em>just work</em>. Otherwise, there is little incentive for a user to even give it a try. Also, there is the part about advocacy and letting people know that alternatives exist which can be way better than the technology people use today. This awareness needs to be built from the ground-up. We cannot just say that “cloud services are evil”. We need to show people real advantages; we need to show people that they do not have to exchange comfort, usability and performance for privacy and security.</p>

<p>We need to make decentralized systems <em>work</em>.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="suggested-readings">Suggested readings</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/tech/elements/the-mission-to-decentralize-the-internet"><em>The mission to decentralize the internet</em></a> - Joshua Kopstein</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.dailydot.com/technology/decentralized-internet-future/"><em>The future of the open internet is decentralized</em></a> - Joseph Cox</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.eff.org/cyberspace-independence"><em>A Declaration of the Independence of Cyberspace</em></a> - John Perry Barlow</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.nationalaffairs.com/public_interest/detail/the-future-computer-utility"><em>The future computer utility</em></a> - Paul Baran</li>
  <li><a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~ldiamond/iraq/Decentralize_Power021204.htm"><em>Why decentralize power in a democracy?</em></a> - Larry Diamond</li>
  <li><a href="http://people.umass.edu/dmkotz/What_Ec_Struc_Soc_08_03.pdf"><em>What economic structure for socialism?</em></a> - David M. Kotz</li>
</ul>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://kaustavdm.in/why-decentralize-technology.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2016 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Privacy in technology]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>Privacy has many facets. The issue of privacy bothers us in today’s ever-more connected world because we do not control its manifestations. We see elaborate privacy policies, bills, laws and rights in place. Yet, it is difficult to build a right privacy-aware system for everyone given that the concept of privacy is highly subjective and is open to interpretations.</p>

<p>Before we dig deeper, let us take a look at a few manifestations of privacy in the domain of data transmission. Consider this:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When we want to share information with others using technology, we are dependent on the technology we use to respect whether the information is delivered only to the intended recipient(s) or whether it is shared intentionally or unintentionally with other non-intended recipients.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If we ask under which conditions can we call such a system as “privacy aware”, there can be multiple interpretations. There would be a set of people who would say that as long as their message reaches their recipients, they do not bother about other issues. Let us keep this set of people aside for a while and consider the other possibilities we may have. For instance, some others would say that as long as no one else (governments, corporations, parents, spouses, Sauron) sees the message and it reaches its recipients, it should be alright. By those terms, when the information is delivered only to the intended recipients, we often call it a “privacy-aware” system. When the information is shared with non-intended recipients, we term it as a “privacy breach”. Some others would argue that this is not good enough. If the system stores the data that they had sent through it, irrespective of whether the system makes use of that stored data now or in future, it violates privacy. An edge group would further add that as long as such a system stores data beyond the duration of the actual transmission, it is a violation of privacy, regardless of the intention.</p>

<p>That is a lot of opinions to take in, and it does not even represent the full spectrum of opinions regarding privacy in one domain. We see three patterns emerging out of this example:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Interpretation of privacy is personal and subjective;</strong> one size does not fit all.</li>
  <li><strong>Many privacy-related issues can get intertwined once you dig deeper;</strong> the way data usage became a concern in data transmission in the scenario above.</li>
  <li><strong>People often exchange privacy with comfort to certain degrees;</strong> based on the amount of facilities offered.</li>
</ul>

<p>I’ll leave the solution for a later exercise. For now, let us focus on the issues at hand and try to understand them in detail.</p>

<h2 id="when-does-privacy-manifest">When does privacy manifest?</h2>

<p>That instinctive uncomfortable feeling we get when someone watches us behind our back perhaps ties back to our survival traits. In an environment where we don’t have to worry about a predator pouncing on us, our instincts evolve to try to figure out who may be watching us, tracking our moves. The demand for privacy rises as our base reaction to protect information of our personal state from such external entities. That is, we like to able to define the terms when we would prefer to remain unobserved by others. This can be for anything — from trying to focus on a problem at hand, having secret conversations, to going on a trip without someone tracking us. The ask changes from “Don’t eat me” to “Leave me alone”. We still remain wary of the predator; except the nature of the predator changes and becomes increasingly harder to uncover.</p>

<p>In technology, the manifestation of privacy appears whenever there is a component of user data involved. We can loosely describe “user data” as any information either actively produced by a user or passively generated by the actions and interactions of the user. User data can be either anonymous or identifiable. Some of these manifestations are apparent and easy to pin-point, some are veiled and seem apparently harmless.</p>

<p>For example, if someone gets unauthorized access to our mobile phones and secretly listens to our conversations, it can be easily pin-pointed as a privacy issue. Yet, when we are under surveillance in public places, it tends to seem alright. In either cases, these systems can access information about us in the form of audio conversations or audio/video feed showing our actions. Both these systems access what I described above as “user data”. Hence, both of these should raise privacy concerns. But, we seem to be less perturbed about public surveillance systems. Why? Maybe because we don’t perceive such observation as threats. Some of us don’t mind being under surveillance, some of us are uncomfortable about it and some of us get downright upset about it.</p>

<p>The point to note here is that even when user data is involved and crucial privacy issues arise, the perception of how much privacy is good privacy remains very much subjective.</p>

<h3 id="why-is-privacy-optional-today">Why is privacy optional today?</h3>

<p>The nature of the technology we see around us today almost always poses a trade-off between sharing user data and facilities offered. You cannot have your intelligent calendar auto-record travel dates as calendar events without reading and understanding your emails. You cannot browse an item on an e-commerce website without every other website showing you targeted advertisements urging you to buy similar products from them.</p>

<p>This is not to say today’s technology is “evil”. It simply means that they offer an exchange. These products and services need human effort and computing cycles to keep them up and running. So, they need money to build and operate. Plus, many of them need surplus money to pay dividends to their shareholders. Where would all these money come from? Either the user pays directly for the services received, or the user pays indirectly by letting the service sell their user data. The first kind tends to respect user data. The second kind, where the users do not pay immediately out of their pockets, become the rabbit hole of privacy leaks. You never know where your data will end up once it has been packaged and sold by one party.</p>

<p>This makes privacy an optional feature in the technology we have today. The more privacy you seek, lesser the number services that match your requirements. You either give up your personal data or do not be part of those systems. Is this a good enough model? Certainly not. But, trying to fix it will require a good amount of forethought and is a big topic in itself, outside the scope of the current discussion.</p>

<h2 id="does-security-guarantee-privacy">Does security guarantee privacy?</h2>

<p>The term “security” in the context of technology roughly expands to the concept of disallowing unauthorized access. Encryption is the first stepping stone in that direction. A lot of nuances of security implementations follow. I like to see security as a fundamental requirement of privacy. But security alone does not guarantee privacy.</p>

<p>Consider this: A social networking system can have industry-leading encryption, can have multi-factor authentication, can serve from militarized data centres, all to ensure that only their authorized members can get through and no authorized members can access or modify personal information of other members. This does not guarantee that the data each member generates will remain within the system. There may be terms stating that user data will be shared with third parties as long as a user continues to be a part of the system. So, even with the highest grade security, you cannot control where your user data ends up from a system like this.</p>

<p>On the other hand, consider a system that does not store user data, does not attempt at sharing or selling user data with third parties, does not track a user through other systems, but does not use any encryption and makes all data exchanges over open networks in plain text. Any agencies looking to gather user data can simply snoop-in on such systems and copy all the data they want. Here, even though the system tried to be privacy aware, lack of security mechanisms prevented it from effectively enforcing its goals.</p>

<p>So, a system that wants to respect privacy must have strong security mechanisms. But, it does not mean that any system with strong security mechanisms is built with user privacy in mind.</p>

<h2 id="blurring-the-boundaries-privacy-in-a-connected-world">Blurring the boundaries: Privacy in a connected world</h2>

<p>Now, let us consider a scenario where all the issues with privacy identified so far appear all the more seriously: A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collective_intelligence">collective intelligence</a>.</p>

<p>A collective intelligence forms through constant collaboration and coordination between different entities. It is built on the principles of openness, peering (instead of hierarchies), sharing and removing regional boundaries. All of these require members of the collective to share what they know, in real-time, to make conscious decisions as a group and to improve the collective itself. It is a constant flow of user data, a constant flux of state, as it progresses through individual contributions. When seen as a whole, a collective intelligence can undermine individuality in favour of the larger goal.</p>

<p>Given the internet we have today, creating a collective intelligence will be a matter of building better real-time data sharing systems and making the internet more seamless as part of our physical existence. It is not a distant future. Can we still ensure there is enough room for privacy in a system like that? Enough to room to assert one’s individuality?</p>

<p>Theoretically, the simplest implementation of privacy in a collective intelligence is a switch that lets you isolate thoughts that you do not wish to share with the collective. This can be a part of a thought-driven interface or even a manual hardware switch. Think of it like an active-state toggle. Without such a device, there would be very less option to retain individuality. Without individuality, you lose the ability to think independently. Without independent thinking, you lose the capability to make progress at an individual level. And, a system that does not make progress, however advanced it may be, eventually regresses.</p>

<hr />

<p>For a connected world that is getting more and more connected each day, it is very important to implement privacy-conscious traits as part of its basic routine, as a core part of the technology that is shaping up this connected state. Without such measures, all the innovations in present and future may not make full use of the analytical aspect of the human mind. We need open, yet, private spaces and technology can be the enabler.</p>

<p><small>Image credit: <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/opengridscheduler/19481515583/">Open Grid Scheduler / Grid Engine on Flickr</a></small>.</p>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://kaustavdm.in/privacy-in-technology.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2016 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What you read is what you become]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h5 id="all-that-noise-in-the-digital-world-is-what-fills-your-mind-do-you-trust-the-world-to-keep-it-neat">All that noise in the digital world is what fills your mind. Do you trust the world to keep it neat?</h5>

<p>Traditional media holds much sway over public perception. Media can make or break people, campaigns, events. A couple of examples:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.indiaenvironmentportal.org.in/files/file/Anna%20Hazare.pdf">Anna Hazare</a> [pdf, 121KB]</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.politico.com/magazine/story/2016/03/donald-trump-2016-media-213695">Donald Trump</a> (proving no publicity is bad publicity)</li>
</ul>

<p>By focusing intensely on topics they want us to notice, media can make us notice certain topics that we wouldn’t otherwise want to notice. Also, by taking up our attention and exhausting it, media prevents us from noticing other things that are worth noticing.</p>

<p>For example, <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/30244505-gujarat-files">Gujarat Files</a>, which’s a scary book about a “<a href="http://www.fox.com/prisonbreak">Prison Break</a>” style state control over citizens, has gone unnoticed by media outlets and therefore wouldn’t be noticed as easily by public.</p>

<p>Media is mostly concerned about what’s newsworthy. And <a href="http://dobelli.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/08/Avoid_News_Part1_TEXT.pdf">news is dangerous and should be avoided</a> [pdf, 0.5MB]. For example, if 100 people die of diabetes on a day there’s no coverage of that, but if the same 100 people die in an accident, the story is all over the news. And therein lies one of <a href="http://dobelli.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/08/Avoid_News_Part1_TEXT.pdf">the many reasons why news isn’t all good</a> [same pdf as above].</p>

<h5 id="if-traditional-media-is-so-dangerous-what-about-the-newer-media">If traditional media is so dangerous, what about the newer media?</h5>

<p>Newer media (social media, instant messaging apps) are <a href="https://medium.com/swlh/how-technology-hijacks-peoples-minds-from-a-magician-and-google-s-design-ethicist-56d62ef5edf3">designed to hijack people’s minds</a>. These are more dangerous than traditional media in that they not only create crap for you to see, but also <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/morning-mix/wp/2014/08/19/how-facebook-and-twitter-control-what-you-see-about-ferguson/">control what you see</a> (censoring, silencing, promoting, being biased, abusing power) and keeps you coming back for the same.</p>

<p>Facebook’s “trending topics” has recently been <a href="http://www.thewrap.com/facebook-trending-topics-are-controlled-by-20-something-millenials/">discussed for possible biases</a> but the entire newsfeed of Facebook is a much more dangerous biased stream.</p>

<p>And, we have not even begun to <a href="http://www.thehindu.com/opinion/columns/a-borderless-economy-that-will-be-controlled/article8581476.ece">politically regulate websites</a>.</p>

<p>The filter bubble is getting stronger by the day. People are having radically different ideas about the same topic because they live in echo chambers where they see what they like and do not see what they do not like.</p>

<h5 id="what-we-can-do-is-to-stop-giving-them-too-much-power">What we can do is to stop giving them too much power</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Stop consuming junk news.</li>
  <li>Quit <a href="http://learnlearn.in/facebook/">Facebook</a>, at least install add-ons like <a href="https://www.eff.org/privacybadger">PrivacyBadger</a> that prevents sites like Facebook from <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2016/5/27/11795248/facebook-ad-network-non-users-cookies-plug-ins">tracking you all over the web</a>.</li>
  <li>Promote good journalism by reading long, insightful articles from investigative journalists.</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.goodreads.com/">Read books</a>.</li>
  <li>Go back and read all the links I put in this post.</li>
</ul>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">http://asd.learnlearn.in/what-you-read-is-what-you-become/</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Akshay S Dinesh]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2016 19:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Farewell 172.17.42.1, you will be missed!]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>A week ago, around 3 in the morning, continuous beeps from alerts slack channel, woke me up. “Logs! My Precious. We wants it!”</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>Apr 05 21:57:32 update_engine[608]: [0405/215732:INFO:update_attempter.cc(283)] Processing Done.
Apr 05 21:57:32 update_engine[608]: [0405/215732:INFO:update_attempter.cc(309)] Update successfully applied, waiting to reboot.
Apr 05 21:57:32 update_engine[608]: [0405/215732:INFO:update_check_scheduler.cc(82)] Next update check in 44m35s
Apr 05 21:57:32 locksmithd[640]: LastCheckedTime=1459893385 Progress=0 CurrentOperation="UPDATE_STATUS_UPDATED_NEED_REBOOT" NewVersion=0.0.0.0 NewSize=186494743
Apr 05 21:57:32 systemd-logind[612]: System is rebooting.
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>Did I just see “System rebooting.” Why? FYI, the machine runs CoreOS. In a while, we came to know CoreOS and the tools it ships are updated automatically as new versions come out. They say “We believe that automatically updating the operating system is one of the best tools to achieve this goal.” Reading more on CoreOS update strategies, the reboot strategy could be defined in cloud-config.</p>

<p>You may opt to disable automatic update daemon. Temporary way would be disabling <code class="highlighter-rouge">update-engine</code> service manually by doing</p>

<p><code class="highlighter-rouge">sudo systemctl stop update-engine</code></p>

<p>.. but this service auto starts on machine reboot. Permanent way would be change the config in <code class="highlighter-rouge">cloud-config</code> file.</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>#cloud-config
coreos:
  units:
    - name: update-engine.service
      command: stop
    - name: locksmithd.service
      command: stop
</code></pre>
</div>

<blockquote>
  <p>Note: <a href="https://github.com/coreos/locksmith">Locksmith</a> is the reboot manager for the CoreOS update engine</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In the above case, you may manually update the machine by doing <code class="highlighter-rouge">update_engine_client -check_for_update</code></p>

<p>But, out of all this, the recommended way would be to do the auto updates with a maintenance window where you define a window of time during which a reboot can occur in the <code class="highlighter-rouge">cloud-config</code> file.</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>#cloud-config
coreos:
  locksmith:
    window-start: Thu 02:00
    window-length: 1h
</code></pre>
</div>

<blockquote>
  <p>Note: In this example, the window is defined to be every Thursday between 02:00 and 03:00</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Well, with the CoreOS things figured out, this chained us to another problem. The host was rebooted and switched over to a later version of docker. After digging deep, we figured, the default <code class="highlighter-rouge">docker0</code> IP is not <code class="highlighter-rouge">172.17.42.1</code> for new installs (&gt; v1.9), anymore. That was just a magic undocumented IP which FWIW we hardcoded it in a few places.</p>

<p>After the change of this IP in docker update, someone even sent a PR to <code class="highlighter-rouge">docker/libnetwork</code> - https://github.com/docker/libnetwork/pull/649/files which has been closed without merging. Obviously! No more magics, they say!</p>

<p>To fix this up, you may follow any of the following ways</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Use <code class="highlighter-rouge">bip</code> flag to provide CIDR notation address for the dynamically created bridge (docker0) <code class="highlighter-rouge">sudo docker daemon --bip="172.17.42.1/16"</code></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Look up your default gateway IP inside the container and whatever IP that is, is the IP that you can use to talk to the host.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>In case you are confused with anything I wrote above, do comment. All hail hydra!</p>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dolftax.com//2016/04/Farewell-171.17.42.1-you-will-be-missed</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Delhi - my city]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[I love cities. And I love them more when they are big and when they do not sleep at night. Maybe it is my love of nights that make me love cities which never sleep. But the fact is, I love cities. Cities are full of life - schools, offices, markets, hospitals, shops, malls, movies, parks, high speed Internet, opportunities, energy, technology, people, government, facilities, sound, lights, and did I miss nightlife? I love it when all the action is around you. And Delhi is the capital of all action. That is why I love Delhi.<br /><br />This was my second time in Delhi. The <a href="http://blog.learnlearn.in/2009/05/what-kerala-and-keralites-can-and-must.html">last time</a> too when I was in Delhi I loved it, albeit a lot less. This time I was talking to my friend who lives in Delhi as if he came to my city and not the other way round. But I am digressing a lot. I need to write about my trip. And it is about time that I finished the entire series. From this point onwards I might not maintain the chronological order of events in my posts, more because I have begun forgetting details and sequences than because the rest of the journey involves me visiting the same places multiple times with different people.<br /><br />We stopped at NOIDA and stayed at my friend's house where we had nice mutton specialities.<br /><br />Next day morning we took to the metro. Got a ₹150 tourist ticket to travel throughout the day. <br /><br />First stop at Akshardham temple (which did exist the last time I came to Delhi, but I didn't know). This is a huge temple built after AD 2000 with "donations" of a large number of devotees. There was marble and gold all over and the story of Swaminarayan. But, because of a previous bomb blast here, to get inside is a huge task. First, you put your mobile phones, ear phones, non-transparent water bottles, etc in your bag. Then you fill a form with your details. Then one person from the whole group should carry all these inside to the baggage counter where they keep the bags "safe". There, this person is supposed to take out all the mobiles and lay them down to count (which is very stupid because in our group we had a lot of phones and I didn't even know where in the bag the phones were when I went to the counter). After showing your face, etc into the camera you get a metal token number. Now, you can all walk to the body checking counter where you have to remove your belt, wallet, etc which will go through a metal detector kind of thing and then get frisked.<br /><br />All this for walking through some marble. I don't know why, but religion immediately colours my view of magnificent structures in a bad shade of greenish-pink.<br /><br />There are many "dwars" (holes) you have to pass through before reaching the central shrine which has very elaborate designs all around. There is water surrounding these areas. Next to the shrine is a statue of Swaminarayan which hosts the lights and sound show in the night.<br /><br />Near the way out I found the most fascinating thing in the whole place. A very large solar panel that moves with the sun such that it gets the maximum sunlight all day! That thing probably powers the entire place. We also had some snacks in the restaurant at the exit. The toilets here are great too!<br /><br />I did come back to Akshardham a second time a few days later. This time we saw the water show. It was splendid, with laser lights being used (unlike just lights in Amber). The laser allowed showing much more delicate things and even animated videos. <br /><br />From Akshardham two of us had gone to Qutb Minar while the rest went to Sarojini Nagar market for shopping. Aeroplanes were constantly trying to hit the Minar and missing it. There was a plaque at the bottom that specified Qutb Minar was shorter than Taj Mahal by 5 feet. We saw the iron pillar that never rusts nearby too. I wanted to send a picture postcard to a friend back in Kerala but couldn't find a post office nearby.<br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-CeyBaZxJ6C8/V33wOvGH2QI/AAAAAAAAMBw/rHjD1d-m3LIJCSkOVCaLMfpHuc98GPDuACLcB/s1600/plane-missing-qutb-minar.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="320" src="https://3.bp.blogspot.com/-CeyBaZxJ6C8/V33wOvGH2QI/AAAAAAAAMBw/rHjD1d-m3LIJCSkOVCaLMfpHuc98GPDuACLcB/s320/plane-missing-qutb-minar.jpg" width="240" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;">Misses it every time.</td></tr></tbody></table><br />We then went to Sarojini Nagar Market where you could buy all things original or all things duplicate as you prefer at costs you decide. We learned bargaining skills, and fell for tricks too. Had nice coffee there. Did a lot of window shopping. Almost got bitten by a dog. Heard a person say "these are stolen items and you get these at unbelievable discounts. No guarantee these will be here tomorrow". Saw so many clothes that you would never buy clothes from anywhere else.<br /><br />That night as I was chatting on my phone my friends came up with a cake singing happy birthday with "Happy Birthday ASD" written on it. I had turned 23. Quite a wonderful birthday this one.<br /><br />Next day I split from this group I was travelling with till now and went to join another set of friends in Delhi, near Jasola Apollo. We had food and by evening went to the Rashtrapati Bhavan. Saw the red soil at Raisina Hill, the canons, etc. up close. Looked at the long Raj Path till India gate choosing not to walk it with our heavy bags.<br /><br />That night we would leave for Uttarakhand, reaching back 5 days later.<br /><br />After returning we had brief visits to Chandini Chowk market, Akshardham (lights &amp; sound show), etc. At Chandini Chowk market we had Dahi Bhalles. But by then, as you will soon learn, our stomachs wouldn't accept most food items.]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-668652011781121325.post-1272747098644339326</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Akshay S Dinesh]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 06:50:11 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Taking the escape route]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>If you keep on blaming the world, and those around you, for things in your life that you consider as unfair, unjust or bad, there are high chances that those were self-afflicted or results of your blatant escapism.</p>

<p>If this is true, you will never learn from your own mistakes. You will always find comfort in putting the blame on others. You will get further detached from the truth. Just because you refuse to see it, doesn’t mean it changes, though you will end up convincing yourself that you were a victim.</p>

<p>Worst of all, you will never know how things would have been if you had the courage to face facts and accept the reality. You may not be aware, but you may be doing this to yourself out of your own volition. So, before you start judging others and broadcasting your ignorance, take a moment to introspect.</p>

<p>For extreme cases, there are clinically recognised <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dissociative_disorder">manifestations</a> of this situation. Having been through such a phase since my childhood, I can vouch that it can be addressed with consistent efforts. Though, this is rarely the reason.</p>

<p>Remember: <strong>Taking the escape route is easy. Reaffirming reality is not.</strong></p>

<p><small>Photo credit: <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/pasukaru76/5796803202/">Chibi Marine Concept</a>.</small></p>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://kaustavdm.in/escape-route.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2016 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Announcing Muktakosh]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://muktakosh.org">Muktakosh</a> is a new non-profit-oriented organization that I, <a href="http://debs.io">Deb</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/pawzoned">Nayanika</a> and a few friends are trying to build. Our focus is on exponential technologies — doing researches which require a good amount of time and effort, and are usually difficult to sustain, and build a strong community of thinkers and doers in the process.</p>

<h2 id="about-the-initiative">About the initiative</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://muktakosh.org/t/topic/8"><strong>About Muktakosh</strong></a>: This discussion talks in brief about what Muktakosh is and what you can engage with at this point.</li>
  <li><a href="https://muktakosh.org/t/topic/31"><strong>Muktakosh mission</strong></a>: This discussion talks about the core mission of Muktakosh.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="muktakosh-at-present">Muktakosh at present</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://muktakosh.org/c/ideas"><strong>Idea hub</strong></a>: The <a href="https://muktakosh.org/c/ideas">Idea Hub</a> in Muktakosh is a place envisioned to foster discussions on technologies, art, design and literature that people want. We have put some of our ideas there to begin with.</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/muktakosh/unicorn/"><strong>unicorn</strong></a>: We have started working on unicorn, a federated connectivity suite, that we have put in the public domain. There is no demo yet, but hoping to have one in 6 months. The <a href="https://muktakosh.org/c/unicorn">discussions</a> happen on Muktakosh.org.</li>
  <li><a href="https://muktakosh.org/t/topic/21"><strong>ConQ</strong></a>: We had planned <a href="https://muktakosh.org/t/topic/21">ConQ</a> during our <a href="http://applait.com">Applait</a> days, as a discussion platform, when we wanted to make a business out of it. Eventually, we felt that it is better off as an open and community driven project, given its goals.</li>
</ul>

<p>Muktakosh.org is built as a discussion platform. Instead of having a landing page, a static mission page etc., we decided to make everything participatory. The entire website is a forum, making participation possible from the very beginning. Even the about and mission pages are open for discussions.</p>

<h2 id="legal">Legal</h2>

<h3 id="have-you-registeredincorporated">Have you registered/incorporated?</h3>

<p>We want to, eventually. Currently, the cost of incorporating and maintaining a legal body is more than the cost of operations for the next 6 months. Till we have further traction in the community, and unless there is a need for a separate legal entity to cover liabilities, we would like to roll lightly.</p>

<h3 id="what-about-ip-rights">What about IP rights?</h3>

<p>We believe concepts like IP rights, patents and copyrights are harmful for free innovation. With that in mind, the IP generated by Muktakosh and its projects are explicitly put under liberal licenses or dedicated to the public domain. Copyright, wherever applicable, are owned by the contributors, but are usually explicitly waived.</p>

<h2 id="what-happens-to-applait">What happens to Applait?</h2>

<p>Applait was built as a for-profit product outfit. We had extremely interesting ideas, some of which we <a href="https://grouphone.me">experimented with</a>. It still remains alive, albeit passive. The ideas will be pursued under the mission of the Muktakosh project.</p>

<h2 id="addendum">Addendum</h2>

<p>Our goal with projects like unicorn and ConQ is to enable unified, ubiquitous communication – free of silos. That was not doable as a business. We have tried. We have talked to people in the industry, to investors, to prospective clients, but our goals did not sync with them.</p>

<p>Think of Wikipedia as a private, for-profit corporation. It wouldn’t have achieved this level of success. It would have needed to pivot to something else to bring in revenues.</p>

<p>The currently proposed organization structure, modus operandi, the projects, the architecture are result of 2 years of discussions and research. We are thinkers and technologists at heart. We would rather see these projects out there, helping others, than make money.</p>

<p>Please do participate, and share it with others who may find it useful.</p>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://kaustavdm.in/announcing-muktakosh.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Mar 2016 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Agra]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<div style="white-space: pre-wrap;">We took the 19'666' Udaipur-Khajuraho express to Agra from Gandhinagar railway station Jaipur. It came right behind the double decker express to Delhi. We took general tickets and later upgraded to sleeper tickets from the train and got allotted the same empty seats we were sleeping in after getting on.<br /><br />Outside Agra Cantonment railway station, there was government approved sightseeing packages with small cabs at ₹750 for half day. We had only one place to visit, actually - the Taj Mahal.<br /><br />Taj is large and Agra is small (like Mysore palace and Mysuru). There are multiple gates to the Taj. We took the one near the red fort. (The red fort of Agra is not the red fort of Delhi as I used to believe. At least, that explains how Shah Jahan could see the Taj Mahal from his prison in red fort where he was put by his son). The crowd of rickshaw riders, camel riders, vendors, guides, and photographers who approach you here is larger than you would expect. We fought our way through to the Taj, yet falling for buying some shoe covers.<br /><br />There is tight security at the entrance. Bags are checked and so are people. The entry ticket was a QR code printed on a rectangular piece of paper. It was scanned at the entrance.<br /><br />Once inside, we got a guide for ₹100 which was cheaper than all the guides outside and also stupid because he didn't "guide" us for more than 10 minutes and also led us into a photographer's ambit. More about that later.<br /><br />There is a row of houses just opposite to the grant entrance gate of Taj Mahal which supposedly belong to the descendants of the sculptors who built the Taj Mahal. The story that Shah Jahan cut the hands of the workers so they wouldn't build another Taj Mahal is most probably a myth. I was imagining how cool their address would be - "House 21, Taj Mahal".<br /><br />The design of Taj Mahal complex is mostly symmetric. For every building on the left, there's a similar building on the right. The Taj Mahal itself looks the same from all four sides. The only asymmetry for us was that when we went, two diagonally opposite minarets were being cleaned because of all the color they've been losing and these were draped in metal stands so the workers could sit on them while scrubbing the white turned yellow marbles with some ancient technology of scientific restoration. The entire Taj seems to have turned as yellow as my teeth and I'm sure the next time I go, it'll be the central dome that is being cleaned like this.<br /><br />There were giant writings on all walls, especially at the darwaza (door). The first look at Taj Mahal from front through this door is quite a moment. The monument is very large, larger than what you would expect from photos. And it just stays there. White. Stone.<br /><br />Just inside there is a large number of photographers telling you how the mobile camera is not as good as their professional camera in capturing both your faces and Taj Mahal's simultaneously. Our guide, at this point, told us the story of how Shah Jahan wanted to build a black Taj behind the white across Yamuna (which is a myth and a fantasy created by a writer later, according to wikipedia) and about how the minarets are inclined by 5 degrees outwards so that in the event of an earthquake they won't fall on the dome, and then he led us to a photographer who would waste our time and vice versa. First, he tells ₹25 per photo. Then he tells, only hard copies. What would one do with printouts? He said he can give soft copies too. We took so many photos. Then we chose 4 photos and he said he can't "waste" a CD for just 4 photos. So we chose to get hard copy of just one group photo and then he got so angry and deleted all the photos he took. I had started walking towards the Taj with one of my friends while this drama was happening because after all, people enjoyed Taj even before photography was invented.<br /><br />There is a long and narrow garden and pool in front of Taj which is well maintained. At just about the right spot for photographs there is an elevated platform. When you walk right from right below the Taj, you reach the free shoe racks to keep your shoes. We turned in all our shoes. Even those of us who had shoe covers. For a moment we thought the shoe cover is a shoe made of cloth to be worn on naked foot, but just as we moved away from the racks we saw others wearing the shoe cover over their shoes. I was walking barefoot anyhow, because I wanted to feel the marble. All of us walked barefoot.<br /><br />There are two paths everywhere. One for general tickets, one for VIP tickets. I assume the VIPs are those foreigners who are forced to pay ₹500 and above. The general entrance is towards the right again. We get to enter the Taj from behind. There are two buildings just flanking the minarets. One of these is a mosque. Among the other buildings in the complex is a VIP guest house where ministers and others can stay when they come to Agra.<br /><br />The marble was cold even though it was around noon when the skin of our feet touched it. Like I said, the general ticket holders enter via the backside and so we saw the Yamuna first. The river flows parallel to the backside of the Taj. There is a garden on the exact opposite bank and nobody can be blamed for thinking Shah Jahan wanted to build a black Taj Mahal for himself there.<br /><br />Once you climb on the platform where the minarets are, you can no longer see the dome and therefore the Taj Mahal becomes so unlike what you know from all the pictures. The symmetry of the construction is mathematical. Yet there is an entrance at the front wall, the marble sides of which are carved with flowers and other designs. The entrance directly leads to the dimly lit tombs of Mumtaj and Shah Jahan. There was a tunnel to go underground where the actual tombs are, but it remains closed now and we can only see representations in the top. The marble here is translucent, as demonstrated in the transilluminence test at a corner by me and many others. There are glass doors everywhere with small round glass arranged like honeycomb on them. People trying to write their name on this glass had broken several of the comb compartments already.<br /><br />We came outside and sat on the marble and under the shade of the marble mausoleum for a while. Yamuna brought breeze. After collecting our shoes and calculating how much money the shoe keeper would get as "happiness allowance", we walked through the less busy side road into the Taj Museum.<br /><br />The museum welcomes you with a read board that describes what it exhibits - coins, maps, letters, pictures, stones. The center piece is this map of the entire Taj Mahal complex which definitely didn't include a black Taj. My hypothesis is that Shah Jahan wanted to build a small house for himself on the other bank where he could sit and watch the Taj Mahal till his death. (Remember Aurangzeb put him in the nearby Red Fort (which is not the Red Fort of Delhi) which had a similar view, probably on his request)<br /><br />We went to the toilets in one corner which is free for foreigners (payback for paying so much to enter) and well maintained. Displayed on the wall outside till the exit, are pictures of various monuments in India pretty many of which I'm yet to see. While exiting, I couldn't fail to notice the awe and wonder on the face of people who were entering then and getting their first glimpse of the Taj. Once outside we had to rush to our car escaping from the e-carts, rickshaws, and camels. And then through the waste-filled gullies of Agra to the inter state bus terminal where we would catch a fast bus that plies on the Yamuna express way to Noida.</div>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-668652011781121325.post-1429614898522014056</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Akshay S Dinesh]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 06:56:36 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[On online activism]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>If signing an online petition is <em>all</em> that you <em>ever</em> do about serious social, environmental, economic or political issues, then neither do you help change the current situation that you are complaining about, nor does it make any real difference.</p>

<p>It is even worse if you have signed those petitions because some of your friends have done the same.</p>

<p>Try to get to the root of the cause, try to understand it, and if you do understand the issue, raise your voice out louder. May be join the larger protests?</p>

<p>If you do not want to be on the streets or be public about your views, why not stay in your comfort zone and try devising actual solutions to these issues? Like raising awareness, instead of just complaining, may be by writing about it, or talking about it to your friends who do not understand the matter in concern very well. Even better, if you are a technologist, maybe you can come up with technology-driven fixes for those issues that can be fixed with better technology.</p>

<p>Why stay inside a sound-proof glass house and try shouting occasionally at the world outside? No one will hear you. They will just see you make weird gestures.</p>

<p>Why not push your limits and try to make a difference?</p>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://kaustavdm.in/online-activism.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2016 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FOSSMeet 2016 @ NIT Calicut - Getting Started Contributing to Mozilla]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>FOSSMeet is an annual event at National Institute of Technology, Calicut for promoting Free and Open Source Software.</p>

<p>This is the notes from my session titled “Getting Started Contributing to Mozilla”.</p>

<p>We aren’t paid to work in Mozilla. Then why do we still contribute to Mozilla?</p>

<p>Because of <a href="https://www.mozilla.org/mission/">Mozilla’s mission</a>. Our mission is to promote openness, innovation &amp; opportunity on the Web.</p>

<p>It is easier to understand Mozilla’s mission if we look at the Internet as a <a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/blog/2016/02/08/the-internet-is-a-global-public-resource/">large public resource</a>. We have built everything conceivable on top of the Internet - communication, social media, e-commerce, banking, ticket booking, education, grocery shopping, food delivery, what you can imagine, you can build. Being such a powerful and useful public resource, there are multiple predators for the Internet. The Internet gets polluted in many ways. It gets attacked by many.</p>

<h2 id="internet-pollution">Internet Pollution</h2>

<p>I call it Internet pollution when something is bad for the Internet.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Large websites full of flash videos, scrolling images, yet inaccessible or useless text on it is a kind of pollution for me.</li>
  <li>Websites that work only when proprietary extensions are installed on a browser, or those which work only in one particular browser.</li>
  <li>Companies trying to monopolize Internet like Airtel, Facebook is polluting the Internet.</li>
</ul>

<p>Mozilla protects the Internet from this pollution.</p>

<p>We keep the Internet a place where things can happen, where you and I can create a website today and make it usable today, where everyone is equal, a place of our dreams.</p>

<h2 id="mozilla-manifesto">Mozilla Manifesto</h2>

<p>At Mozilla we believe in a set of principles and values. Read the <a href="https://mozilla.org/about/manifesto">mozilla manifesto</a>.</p>

<p>If you agree with our principles, you are a Mozillian!</p>

<h2 id="contribute">Contribute</h2>

<p>There are a hundred ways you can contribute to Mozilla. I’ll outline the most important and <a href="http://asd.learnlearn.in/mozilla-impact/">impactful</a> ways to do so.</p>

<h3 id="technical">Technical</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Code for Firefox
    <ul>
      <li>Desktop</li>
      <li>Android</li>
      <li>iOS</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Work with out <a href="http://ateam-bootcamp.readthedocs.org/en/latest/">automation team (ateam)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/Add-ons">Develop add-ons for Firefox</a></li>
  <li>Learn <a href="https://www.rust-lang.org/">rust</a>, write libraries</li>
  <li>Use Firefox OS for IoT hardware</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.mozilla.org/firefox/channel/">Test beta versions</a></li>
  <li>A lot more projects</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="non-technical">Non-technical</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Documentation - for example, <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/">Mozilla Developer Network</a> needs technical as well as language review.</li>
  <li><a href="https://l10n.mozilla.org">Localization</a> - translate Firefox into your language</li>
  <li><a href="https://support.mozilla.org">User support</a> - help others online</li>
  <li><a href="https://advocacy.mozilla.org">Advocacy</a> - Campus campaign on encryption, privacy, accessibility, net neutrality, etc.</li>
  <li><a href="https://teach.mozilla.org/">Mozilla Learning Network</a> - Form mozilla clubs, organize events, teach people how to wield the web.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.mozillascience.org/">Mozilla Science lab</a> - Making research collaborative, accessible, and usable.</li>
</ul>

<p>Please form a Firefox Club in your college</p>

<h2 id="communication-channels">Communication Channels</h2>

<p>We have a lot of communication channels in Mozilla. Please join the chat at these very important places:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://discourse.mozilla-community.org">Our discourse</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/about/forums/">Interesting mailing lists</a> - careful, there are a lot of lists here and many are super active while some are hyper-inactive</li>
  <li><a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/IRC">IRC</a></li>
  <li>There are some channels on Telegram too, which you can <a href="http://asd.learnlearn.in/about/#contact">contact me</a> to get added to.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="tools">Tools</h2>

<p>There are two important tools you need to get acquainted with</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org">Bugzilla</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/mozilla">Github</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="more-links">More links</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.mozilla.org/contribute/">mozilla.org/contribute</a> - sign up here and that’s all you need to do</li>
  <li><a href="http://whatcanidoformozilla.org">whatcanidoformozilla</a> - find out what you can do</li>
  <li><a href="http://www.joshmatthews.net/bugsahoy/">bugsahoy</a> - find bugs to work on (there’s a special search feature to find easy bugs)</li>
  <li><a href="https://mozillians.org">mozillians</a> - sign up for a Mozillian account and be a Mozillian</li>
</ul>

<p>You can always reach out to me at <a href="https://mozillians.org/u/asdofindia">mozillians.org/u/asdofindia</a></p>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">http://asd.learnlearn.in/fossmeet-2016/</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Akshay S Dinesh]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2016 04:33:45 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Talk: Kranky Geek WebRTC event in Bangalore]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>I’ll be speaking about the state of WebRTC in Firefox at <a href="https://www.krankygeek.com/">Kranky Geek’s WebRTC event</a> in Bangalore on March 19, 2016.</p>

<p>Here is the talk abstract:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Mozilla is a strong proponent of decentralized, privacy-aware communications, and the principles behind WebRTC align very closely with the Mozilla mission. Mozilla has launched “Firefox Hello” last year, a WebRTC driven live video chat system that now ships with the Firefox web browser. This talk will explore the path ahead for WebRTC implementations in Firefox and it will show what is already available in the latest Firefox nightly through some demos.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/kranky-geek-webrtc-bengaluru-show-2016-tickets-20440274411">Tickets</a> for this event are available for free. So, grab yours!</p>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://kaustavdm.in/talk-krankygeek-bangalore.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2016 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Zen of Open Source]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0020/">Zen of Python</a> has been my inspiration in programming from the early days. I have even found some of its principles priceless in daily life. After nearly a decade of involvement with the Open Source world, this is my humble attempt at jotting down the “Do’s and Don’ts” of the Open Source world in the style of The Zen of Python. Consider this to be a tribute to <a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0020/">PEP-0020</a>.</p>

<p>This post consolidates the thoughts of <a href="http://hintjens.com/blog:43">Pieter Hintjens</a>, <a href="http://brunorocha.org/10-rules-of-open-source-projects.html">Bruno Rocha</a> and <a href="http://fossforce.com/2010/05/the-zen-of-open-source/">Christine Hall</a> on Open Source, and adds some of my experience to it.</p>

<h2 id="the-zen-of-open-source">The Zen of Open Source</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Open is better than closed.</li>
  <li>Explicit license is better than implicit intention.</li>
  <li>Public domain is better than copyleft.</li>
  <li>Copyleft is better than copyright.</li>
  <li>Small team is better than working alone.</li>
  <li>Community is better than a small team.</li>
  <li>Documentation counts.</li>
  <li>Special projects aren’t special enough to file patents.</li>
  <li>Although practicality beats ideologies,</li>
  <li>Patches should never be ignored silently,</li>
  <li>Unless they break tests.</li>
  <li>In the face of ambiguity, refuse the temptation to close an issue.</li>
  <li>There should be one– and preferably only one –style guide.</li>
  <li>Although that way may not be obvious at first unless you’re a bot.</li>
  <li>Incomplete project is better than none.</li>
  <li>Although never is often better than <em>yet-another</em> library that reinvents the wheel.</li>
  <li>If the code is unreadable or archaic, it’s a bad idea.</li>
  <li>If the code is idiosyncratic but has documentation, it may be a good idea.</li>
  <li>Tests are one honking great idea – let’s do more of those!</li>
</ul>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://kaustavdm.in/the-zen-of-open-source.html</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2016 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Pink City]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<div style="white-space:pre-wrap">Jaisalmer Delhi express reaches Jaipur by 5 in the morning. Even if it is late at Jodhpur Junction by an hour. Maybe we were too fascinated by the consummation of train 14660 (ours) by 14662 (Malani express) to think about how trains can run fast and catch up on lost time. It works like this. Our train reaches platform 2 of Jodhpur Junction by around 11. We can then get down and go to platform 1 to have tea and refreshments. That is when you can realize your worst fear of seeing your train move forward with your luggage but without you. Soon, our train comes to our platform, in reverse, as if it remembered you and came back to pick you up. But it has actually come to pick up the coaches from Malani express which has been waiting there. And since this has to happen necessarily, railways will reschedule the departure for you to have your tea without worries even if the arrival was late.<br><br>So, how do you wake up on time even though your alarms were scheduled an hour late? Enter North Indian aunties. They talk lovingly to each other at decibels higher than our alarms. And fortunately we had a double family next to our berths. They woke their children up and explained how Jaipur is coming up in half an hour and all I had to do was wake up and listen.<br><br>First thing you notice when you are on the roads of Jaipur is how wide, clean, and organized (straight) they are. We would later hear in the lights and sound show at the Amber fort that Jaipur is the first planned city in India, as we guessed.<br><br>At Jaipur, we stayed at the guest house of my friend&#39;s uncle&#39;s institution. We got some more sleep, then got up, dressed like summer, and set out in the car that was arranged for us. <br><br>We were traveling through Jawaharlal Nehru Marg  when I found out all interesting things on either side of the road with the <a href="http://maps.me">maps.me</a> app on my phone. Most interesting of these was the ruins of a fort just over the white Birla Mandir. This fort apparently has a temple which opens only once in an year and that&#39;s the only time public can go there. Actually, good for the fort because it looked dilapidated.<br><br>Then, Sawai Mansingh (SMS) Medical College, the government medical college of Jaipur that is the counterpart of our college in Mysore, by appearance, location, importance, and even the fact that the hospital and college are on either side of the road like in MMC. Must be endearing, there is a small crowd of MMC undergraduates doing post graduation here, including one of our Malayali seniors who came to meet us when we were shopping in the Jaipur market later that night.<br><br>The only association I had with Jaipur apart from it being the capital of Rajasthan and being called the Pink City was that Hawa Mahal is an important attraction here. But apparently Hawa Mahal is just the windows of an otherwise unremarkable building. And we literally didn&#39;t even step out of the car to take photos.<br><br>But right behind Hawa Mahal are the interesting places we spent time till lunch. (One good thing to note here is that there is a composite ticket for many places available and there is even a student discount if you carry your identity card.) First, the City Palace. At the entrance to this place was sitting a snake charmer and his two hypnotized cobras posing for photos with foreigners. The gate he was sitting in front of was so elaborate we took some photos there, even including the police officer who was standing guard. The City Palace is a fairly large place and we saw the numbering of audio guide spots in the wrong order so there is a definite chance we missed seeing many things. But we definitely saw many interesting leftovers of the royal past. Two giant vessels with tiny wheels, used for carrying water while the king was traveling, made out of melted silver coins. Among other armory, a special kind of dagger you can play with wearing it like Wolverine claws and when you pull on the bar with your curled fingers, the covering sheath of it would slide away to both sides pushing out the knife within. Totally oversized clothes of kings, pyjamas that could accommodate an elephant (probably belonging to Madhosingh who was that large according to sources). Pashmina carpets. Huge chandeliers above the hall where royal proceedings used to happen - surrounded by the portraits and brief history of all the kings that ruled there and the wall paintings of Krishna. (The wikipedia article on the palace describes even more things which I should have read when it mattered)<br><br>Right outside is Jantar Mantar - the collection of astronomical instruments that are large enough to climb on. We went in the reverse order as usual, and without a guide, so we didn&#39;t have to learn any broken science that the guides were feeding the foreigners. Most of the instruments I could figure out did one of the two things - tell time, find the declination or azimuth of an astronomical structure. The largest sundial gave the most accurate timing (local time off by up to two seconds) because that&#39;s the way shadows work. We were not allowed to go near the markings of the large sundial and so we couldn&#39;t read the small markings. The large markings were visible from far away yet we couldn&#39;t find out the time correctly. It was around 1 when we were there but the shadow had crossed more than 2 markings. The local time could definitely not be off by more than half an hour from IST. Something was wrong, yet we took some photos climbing on the walls opposite and still being unable to get the whole dial inside frame. There were smaller dials facing different directions next to the large dial. These would be useful in different seasons when Sun moves around. After passing through many more instruments clueless we reached the dial which was shaped cylindrical with two flat ends facing North and South and sloped in the angle of the slope of the Earth&#39;s equator. This dial had the 24 hour markings in addition to the markings that didn&#39;t add up earlier. That is when the search pages started loading and I confirmed my hunch that the unit of time for the users of these instruments was gatis and palas, and not hours. One day would be divided into ghatis and then into palas and so on. And that would explain everything.<br><br>Having figured it out we came outside, had mutka kulfis, and went towards our next destination - forts. On the way we saw from the road the Jal Mahal which is a palace in the middle of a lake. Didn&#39;t see any boats to reach there, though.<br><br>The Jaigarh fort and the Amber fort are adjacent to each other. In fact, the right way to visit them both would be to reach one and travel through the ancient path into the other. There were military personnel on the way and there seems to be some kind of Indian Air Force activity happening here. <br><br>We reached Jaigarh fort first. Jaivana, the largest cannon in the world was right in front of us and we thought that was all there is to this fort. We walked around looking at holes in the ground figuring out which of them are tunnels and which are water ways. There were also holes in the walls in the characteristic shape of fort wall holes with large opening inside and small opening outside. And there were monkeys and pigeons everywhere. We were hungry and there was a restaurant inside the fort which didn&#39;t exactly look attractive. So we decided to go back down the hill but I curiously went to the other end of the courtyard and saw a board showing directions to a lot of places inside the fort. We had missed almost the entirety of the fort. The King&#39;s palace, the Queen&#39;s place, the giant courtyard where the soldiers would line up, the large water tank. The dining rooms where there were fully dressed up mannequins dining rubber chappathis, green grass in green gardens. <br><br>As soon as we entered a guard there self appointed himself as our guide insisting that he be not paid if we aren&#39;t happy - an offer that is difficult to refuse. He led us into the above places and more. The Jaigarh fort is located higher on the hill than the Amber fort. Jaigarh fort housed soldiers while Amber fort housed the King and Queen. When the King is with the soldiers preparing for war, the Queen might decide to pay a visit. Then, she is transported in pallaquin from Amber fort to Jaigarh fort. At the entrance of the Jaigarh fort from that side is an elaborate Bhool Bulaiya (maze) of pathways which is designed to confuse enemies. We saw the path to Amber fort, the gardens and courtyards inside it, and identified even some locations where Jodha Akbar was shot from the balconies (or watch houses) of the Jaigarh fort.<br><br>The balconies also gave a splendid view of Jaipur city between the hills surrounding it. And the water system that was in place for the forts. There was a small lake at the base of the hill. Rainwater would be collected in this river which is then carried up by elephants into water tanks high above. The tanks have outlets connected to the irrigation system and the gardens below are watered with the same. <br><br>There was a gallery in the central courtyard of Jaigarh fort with photographs of the army and Kings in various moments of twentieth century. Turns out, even after independence, the kings had formidable power for a while. On the opposite side there was a gallery of armors in which the most interesting exhibit was a &quot;time bomb&quot; which looked more like a large cracker with a long safe thread to burn.<br><br>Next we went to Amber fort, having in mind some spots discovered earlier in the aerial view. We had some nice tea at the entrance of this fort. There were writings about the structures in the front yard and we didn&#39;t take a guide. The large front courtyard was where the public could come to meet the king. Around the courtyard there were toilets (which were vertical holes on the ground), massage parlors, baths, and balconies. The paths everywhere were highly interconnected - you could directly go to many rooms from wherever you were standing. <br><br>Amber fort might be the more beautiful of the two. Fountains dripping water in front of a palace full of mirrors, pigeons taking bath in them. Gardens, facing a marble stage where dance and entertainment could take place. Better view points and more photogenic spots, especially when you climb up on either sides to the roof. All you have to be careful is not to tear your jeans by running faster than the high steps allow you to.<br><br>At the exit there are gift shops some playing nice Rajasthani music. There are also independent vendors who sell expensive, so called hand drawn, paintings (the same paintings which we found out in the hands of another vendor later after lights and sound show), cheap fancy earrings, key chains, and bangles.<br><br>We were hungry by then and went down to the city below to have some nice cheap kulchas and pachoris. We were eating right outside the lower gate of the Amber fort from which we could go to the lights and sound show. There are two shows everyday - English first, Hindi next. We chose English but we were running through the long stony route to reach the spot on time. The show hadn&#39;t begun but we didn&#39;t take tickets from the counter below, rather choosing to pay the ticket checker directly since he said that will be better than going down and taking the tickets now that the show was about to start. But this might have cost us dearly as we paid ₹200 per head whereas wikitravel says there&#39;s discount for Indians and students. What made me not doubt the cost was the website which showed the costs and a phone call to the enquiry desk which both said the fee was ₹200. <br><br>Anyhow, the lights and the sounds were all realistic. Different parts of the forts would be lit in different colors and the lights would dance in perfect synchronization with the sounds - of battles, feuds, celebrations, marriages, Kings, soldiers, horses, swords, just, unjust - of history. At the end of it I was cold because of the night and calm because of the happy ending after all the tumult. There was a road till the place from the other side and we didn&#39;t have to run to the place on the way there, we were told by that same ticket collector. On the way out, we went to the toilet where, unusually, the gents had a queue and the ladies didn&#39;t. Then we got into our car right there, no walking, no running.<br><br>We had some time left to go shopping in Jaipur market. Jaipur must be famous for cotton saris because we bought some 5 saris among ourselves. Our train was early morning next day so we hit the sacks early after packing all new things.</div>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-668652011781121325.post-1153844369136083356</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Akshay S Dinesh]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2016 20:34:29 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Golden City]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<div style="white-space: pre-wrap;">The Jodhpur Jaisalmer express is perfect for traveling from Jodhpur to Jaisalmer (duh) overnight. It leaves from Jodhpur junction itself which is large, colorfully lit, and has an escalator. And you reach Jaisalmer railway station around 6 in the morning which is cold enough to warrant monkey cap, gloves, jacket, and shoes to be worn while going to sleep in winter.<br /><br />We had booked stay in Oasis Sam desert camp through <a href="http://goibibo.com/">goibibo.com</a> and it was very cheap for us because of all the credits my friend's brother had saved up. The camp people themselves helped us hire a Bolero jeep to travel. But the check-in time wasn't till 3. So, we went checked in at a hotel near railway station, slept a little, had some nice tea, and freshened up till it was warm enough to go outside.<br /><br />First, we had breakfast at a restaurant nearby. Chola bhattura, parathas, some more nice tea. They played some Rajasthani folk music in the background on request. And the golden Jaisalmer fort was right outside so we took some selfies.<br /><br />While still adjusting to the golden glow on the buildings that the limestone gives off on morning sunlight, we reached at the bottom of Gadi Sagar lake. There's a small walk to the waterfront which is filled with colorful Rajasthani clothes, handiwork, embroidery, etc. That is also where I noticed the animals - dogs, goats - all of which had thick fur, acclimatized to the lazy cold weather of the desert land.<br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-ES9HYClCKME/V33to5QHcLI/AAAAAAAAMBU/G-iXcwUYf6oH3hNMBK03DSrwOL8F0rq-gCLcB/s1600/embro.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="320" src="https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-ES9HYClCKME/V33to5QHcLI/AAAAAAAAMBU/G-iXcwUYf6oH3hNMBK03DSrwOL8F0rq-gCLcB/s320/embro.jpg" width="320" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;">Colourful, no?</td></tr></tbody></table><div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"></div>There is a small temple on the bank of the lake, golden in color as you would have guessed. You can remove your shoes and walk inside. I stayed outside looking at the man who was sitting at the entrance dressed like a sadhu welcoming people with "Jai Shriram" and other mantras (like Mickey Mouse figures in Disney world). There are what look like extensions of the temple in the lake, popping up from the water like somebody built a large temple and then the lake flooded it till just below the top. These were fully occupied by pigeons and the floor with their shit. The water was home to catfish so large that they probably could eat the pigeons if one of them fell into the water. These fishes were being fed dough by some people at the shore. That's apparently one of the main activities here apart from boating. And taking photos, of course.<br /><br />Next, we went to the Jaisalmer fort. We were swamped by guides as soon as we reached. They do have ID cards but they do charge a lot if you don't bargain. We didn't take a guide till we walked about 200 metres from the parking spot to just inside the entrance of the fort. It's actually a good idea to do impulse control and see around for more before you pay money anywhere in Rajasthan, more so in Delhi. Although, if you take this to the extreme you will also find very cheap guides who also don't tell you a lot of things - like we found at Taj Mahal later.<br /><br />The Jaisalmer fort is a live city surrounded by three layers of walls. A quarter of the population of Jaisalmer live inside the fort in their golden houses. The inhabitants are the descendants of the same people who lived in the fort in the past. A part of the fort was for the Warriors (who eat non-vegetarian), another for the Brahmins (who eat vegetarian), and a third part for the Royals (who ate "mixed vegetables" in the words of our guide). Now, many parts have been taken over by restaurants who sell the same kinds of foods.<br /><br />There are two palaces inside the fort - King's palace and Queen's palace. You see a lot of armors in the King's palace. Everything ranging from bows and arrows to guns. And then the short heighted bed which the King would sleep in (so that he doesn't get killed by anyone hiding under it), the halls where he would listen to people, and many other rooms with a lot of architecture. At one place our guide told us that the fort was built with limestone mostly but there's one more kind of stone used rarely - "fossil" stones (I think that's what he told), and it had magical properties like "being able to turn milk into curd overnight".<br /><br />At the roof of the palace you can see all around Jaisalmer. We had some masala chai and turned 360 degrees again and again listening to the guide and seeing the desert, the Pakistan border, the roads, the houses, the desert, and more of the desert. After getting down we found the route to the large canon on the other side of the fort. The canon was also at a height letting us watch the city and our jeep and five guides converging on new groups that arrive. We sat there for more than 15 minutes taking photos and enjoying the breeze.<br /><br />Back near the parking spot we had some chole kulchas which were the best. And then we set forth for Sam.<br /><br />Sam is around 40 km from Jaisalmer and I slept through most of the wind turbines and sand. The place is full of desert camps, camel safari, and other desert adventures. We reached our camp just after noon and we were the only people there then.<br /><br />The tents are surprisingly well furnished. The beds, blankets, and carpets look just like any hotel. But the walls are made of layers of clothes. The door is just another cloth with ropes on the sides allowing you to tie it to the wall around (if you want to "lock" the room). The windows are improvised curtains which can be folded up by pulling the ropes on their sides and unfolded by pulling the ropes in the reverse direction. Another door on the far wall leads you to the bathroom which has solid walls on the other three sides and cloth roof. The floor was tiles. The water was salty. The bathroom was roomy, but I didn't take bath because it was very cold and I didn't wake up in time for the geyser next day.<br /><br />There were about 50 tents like these arranged in a quadrilateral in our camp. The tents on one edge were actually solid rooms unlike our Swiss tents. In the middle there was a platform surrounded by chairs where the cultural programs would happen at the night. The common dining hall was at one corner.<br /><br />We sat enjoying the architecture of our tents and putting socks and towels to dry on the guy ropes while others, mostly families, started filling up other tents one by one.<br /><br />An hour before sunset it was time for us to move to the dunes at the opposite side of the road. The camp had arranged tickets for us in the ship of the desert to travel to the sunset point. We had 4 camels - Michael Jackson, Lucky, Bubloo, and Salman Khan. I was sitting on Lucky with my friend. Getting on a camel is easy since it lies down with its legs folded and you can climb like you climb on a bike. But once you're seated, the camel gets up to its full height - hind legs first - and you have to hold on like Titanic is sinking head first. Pretty much the same when getting down or when walking down a sand dune. At all other times you can actually swing your hips with the camel's and dance in that rhythm without holding anywhere.<br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-PsIuuQRuvvw/V33ugpM8L3I/AAAAAAAAMBg/FJ4mjCI5HT0oGqrsXq1NyQHl7sOBc8legCLcB/s1600/camels-low.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="240" src="https://1.bp.blogspot.com/-PsIuuQRuvvw/V33ugpM8L3I/AAAAAAAAMBg/FJ4mjCI5HT0oGqrsXq1NyQHl7sOBc8legCLcB/s320/camels-low.jpg" width="320" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;">Not posing</td></tr></tbody></table><br />The ride was fun so we paid them extra to take us a bit farther to the "old Pakistan border" where we saw an old bunker and a wire fence and more sand. We saw the sunset on a "private dune", playing with the sand and running barefoot from dune to dune. After sunset it got cold very fast and the sounds of cultural programs could be heard. So we returned to the camp where we were greeted in traditional Rajasthani style by a lady in Rajasthani clothes putting tilak on our forehead.<br /><br />The cultural programs had started on the platform in the middle of the camp. People were seated around in chairs, and on the platform on diwans with masand. We drank some hot tea and ate some snacks sitting down. There were two singers, and drummers, and kartal players, and dancers. The songs were in Hindi and Rajasthani. The main singer also sang some shayariyas in Hindi which were really funny when translated to English for me. The dancers did Rajasthani folk with characteristic hip movements. They also did a few tricks by picking up notes and stones from the floor bending over back with their mouth and eyes, respectively. The lead singer then took over the kartals and did a wonderful performance along with the dolak. Rajasthani kartal is very simple - two flat wooden planks slightly longer than an iPhone 6+. You hit these together very fast, at various sound levels and you get music that sounds almost like tap dance. In fact, the performer was moving in such a way that it appeared like he was dancing with his hands and corresponding music came from in between his fingers. There was also a man who played with fire - swallowing it, blowing fire from his mouth, etc.<br /><br />People started dancing from the beginning and every time someone would get up to dance the singers would ask them to sit down and wait for their chance at the end. Something that irked me was when people used to give the performers money while they were performing. For example, when the lead dancer was dancing with pots on her head and balancing on glasses at the foot, people would come and put money which she would hold between her teeth. After all professional performances, they put random songs and everyone started dancing while some, including us, went to the dining hall for dinner. The dinner was nice buffet. And there were many curries whose names I don't know.<br /><br />After dinner we went and danced till it was too cold and we went to our tents and sat talking.<br /><br />Towards the night the welcome hosts came with tea and sent us off to the night desert. We walked up to the dunes, this time against colder breezes. At the top of a dune, we just lied down on the sand watching the stars (also crossing it off the bucket list of one of us). I stared into the Pakistan side thinking of soldiers at Siachen glacier for a while with the breeze making that eerie sound you hear in mountains. We then went back to our tents, had more tea, and slept. The hosts couldn't arrange camp fire because nobody else was interested and the guy who promised he would arrange it if we wanted slept by the time we went back.<br /><br />The blankets kept us in the bed for longer than we wanted to. We woke up when our jeep driver came looking for us so he could catch his next riders. After having a quick delicious breakfast we packed our bags back to Jaisalmer. This time going back I was awake to see all the wind turbines. Apparently these provide a lot of electricity in Jaisalmer.<br /><br />We went back to the same hotel as last day, and stay put till noon rearranging clothes, munching snacks, settling accounts. We divided into two then and the first pack including me went shopping in the Jaisalmer market - carpets, clothes, and so on. The second pack joined us outside patwa ki haveli. We had bhelpuri and went inside. The entry fee to the building was ₹100 and so we didn't go inside, rather took photos from outside. We then had to run for our train to Jaipur, so we got some food parcel and ran.</div>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-668652011781121325.post-5170419589837131077</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Akshay S Dinesh]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 05:54:50 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Blue City]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<div style="white-space: pre-wrap;">Jodhpur Express left Bangalore City Junction at ten to ten in the night of 27th. It would take about 43 hours to reach Bhagat Ki Kothi (which is to Jodhpur Junction what Yeshwantpur railway station is to SBC.)<br /><br />When I woke up in the morning, we were near Hubli. And when I woke up again, we were still near Hubli. That's when I decided Karnataka was too large and went back to sleep.<br /><br />The men were playing a card game called 'Mongoose' which is just another name for 'Donkey'. The way they distributed the cards was different though. Instead of dealing cards one by one to each person, there was an open deal in which each person pulled out a card to their hand in turns. If the card is one higher than the topmost card of any other player's hand, it could be placed on that other player's hand instead of our own. Thus distribution of cards itself became a game.<br /><br />We bought two decks of card that night and played mongoose, bluff, and even that card trick about "387 years ago there lived A Queen who was 64 years old and had 2 children - Jack and King who were 10+9 and 5 years old respectively".<br /><br />We had home food packaged and ready to eat, everywhere. So all we had to buy from outside was local specialties. Aloo samosa and Bhaji from Gujarat and Rabdi.<br /><br />Rabdi was from Abu Road railway station (which is where you get down to go to Mount Abu). Rabdi is a sweet which you get by concentrating all the goodness of a Litre of milk into an ounce. <br /><br />We reached Mumbai a couple of hours before midnight. And the widely popular Mumbai local trains were plying along ours with a hundred people hanging from its doors.<br /><br />Rajasthan was as green as any other state. Acres of farms on either side of the rail line. Crops which I have no idea as to what they are.<br /><br />The train went at 95 km per hour for around 3 hours straight going into Jodhpur. And we reached just in time for baraat.<br /><br />Before going to baraat, one has to wear the pagadi which is a colorful turban. If untied and unfurled the pagadi will be perhaps as long as a sari and as difficult to tie back into shape (which I realized when I removed it posing for a photo later in the night and had to wear it like a shawl ever after).<br /><br />Dressed up, the groom and his party leave for the bride's place. The groom on a horse with a sword by his belt while everyone else dancing in front, between the music and lights walking around. The actual marriage was in the wee hours of the next day which we slept through at the hotel so we could explore the city in the morning.<br /><br />Umaid Bhawan Palace. That's where the auto drivers took us first. Umaid Singh had this palace inaugurated by 1944. Speaking of Umaid Singh, he was the chief scout of Marwar state, King of the same, and also died of appendicitis shortly after independence. He built the rail lines to Jodhpur to bring marbles and other materials for the palace and that's how Jodhpur got its train lines. He built the airport in Jodhpur because he was an aviation enthusiast.<br /><table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"><tbody><tr><td style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-mDQW8giNM98/V33vnj5rhPI/AAAAAAAAMBs/ZJgQxJr8SK0kYM_03uSqO-cq7rcodJpqACLcB/s1600/umaid-low.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><img border="0" height="240" src="https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-mDQW8giNM98/V33vnj5rhPI/AAAAAAAAMBs/ZJgQxJr8SK0kYM_03uSqO-cq7rcodJpqACLcB/s320/umaid-low.jpg" width="320" /></a></td></tr><tr><td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;">Neat place to live in, huh?</td></tr></tbody></table><br />And he also made me wonder whether development can come in a democracy, whether autocratic rulers are a necessary evil to get things done. Maybe back when machines weren't as plenty as today and all construction had to be done by human labor (along with animal labor), Kings, dictators and their unjust rules would make sure some work gets done, but today machines can replace human effort and therefore it must be possible even in an egalitarian society to build huge structures.<br /><br />The palace is now divided into three. The museum open to public which we visited, the Taj hotel (which contains the swimming pool) and that part where the royal family resides. The museum too is closed to public when the royal family celebrates birthday. North India hits your head with the fact that birth privilege based hierarchical society is not a distant past.<br /><br />Inside the palace museum is the architecture, paintings, wood work, etc. There are photographs showing various political moments in the history, Jodhpur Polo team and their trophies, and so many details of the history. Then there is a dining room where many high profile people dined and where the menu was exotic. Also is a room full of clocks (time pieces) embedded on small scale replicas of all sorts of things - ships, submarines, guns, buildings.<br /><br />Outside there is a garden which we can't walk over and this collection of old luxury cars. So many Rolls Royce cars that the Mercedes Benz car at the end felt like market car. Most of these cars look long and large with their wheels very far apart towards the ends of the body unlike in today's cars.<br /><br />We had kesar kulfi and koffee on the way out. Funny it was served by the same person who was guiding us in the palace with nobody asking him to. In fact, when we had told him that we didn't need a guide he said in Hindi, "If you are happy at the end, give me some money, otherwise I'm just happily helping you here for free", a refrain we heard throughout Rajasthan.<br /><br />Then the waiting autos took us to Mehrangarh Fort. This was one of the many forts we would visit in the next few days. There was a lot of intricate designs in phool ki mahal, sheesh ki mahal, and moti ki mahal (palace of flowers, mirrors, and pearls, respectively) but not very memorable. In between, near the palace of the Queen, we found a large closed door with some steps leading to it where we sat and took some pictures.<br /><br />On the way back from the fort, there was this small lake and marble temple where the King was worshiped. And in the courtyard a man in typical Rajasthani costume was playing the Ravanahatha which is a stringed instrument (violin, cello, etc having been inspired from this) that now fills all the forts with an ambient music.<br /><blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-version="7" style="background: #fff; border-radius: 3px; border: 0; box-shadow: 0 0 1px 0 rgba(0 , 0 , 0 , 0.5) , 0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0 , 0 , 0 , 0.15); margin: 1px; max-width: 658px; padding: 0; width: 99.375%;"><div style="padding: 8px;"><div style="background: #F8F8F8; line-height: 0; margin-top: 40px; padding: 50.0% 0; text-align: center; width: 100%;"><div style="background: url(data:image/png; display: block; height: 44px; margin: 0 auto -44px; position: relative; top: -22px; width: 44px;"></div></div><div style="color: #c9c8cd; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 17px; margin-bottom: 0; margin-top: 8px; overflow: hidden; padding: 8px 0 7px; text-align: center; text-overflow: ellipsis; white-space: nowrap;"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/BBKZ2lhFMLI/" style="color: #c9c8cd; font-family: Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 14px; font-style: normal; font-weight: normal; line-height: 17px; text-decoration: none;" target="_blank">A video posted by Akshay S Dinesh (@asdofindia)</a> on <time datetime="2016-01-30T12:05:57+00:00" style="font-family: Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 17px;">Jan 30, 2016 at 4:05am PST</time></div></div></blockquote><script async="" defer="" src="//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js"></script> Hungry, we had to go to Gypsy restaurant which was the first recommendation by at least two people. But it was too late for lunch and too early for dinner and so we went to another place the rickshaw drivers suggested and had chola bhattura, golgoppa, etc.<br /><br />The Jodhpur market was on the same road. Clothes, spices, and other things to buy that reminded me of DD Urss road back at Mysore. Except Jodhpur has a colorful clock tower at the spicy end of the road. We also went to 'On The Rocks' which was a nice, though slightly expensive place to hang out, to waste some time till our train to Jaisalmer.</div>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-668652011781121325.post-6665674883231356624</guid>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Akshay S Dinesh]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2016 06:50:57 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Renderer - Main process communication in Electron]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://electron.atom.io">Electron (or) Atom Shell</a> is used to build cross platform desktop apps with web technologies. With electron, you can do a lot more than just wrapping your webpage into an app. In browsers, web pages usually run in a sandboxed environment and are not allowed access to native resources. Electron have the power to use Node.js APIs in web pages allowing lower level operating system interactions. Well, how does this work?</p>

<p>Electron exposes <code class="highlighter-rouge">ipc</code> module which allows you to communicate with the operating system. If you have worked with <a href="http://socket.io">socket.io</a> , the pattern looks similar. <code class="highlighter-rouge">ipc</code> works based on <a href="https://nodejs.org/api/events.html">Event Emitter</a> architecture.</p>

<p>Consider an example case where you got a webpage which when accessed from the app, should display the list of folders in a given directory, but from browser, should say “You gotta install our app for this feature”.</p>

<p>First, let’s detect whether the loaded environment is browser (or) app. In the webpage check this condition, <code class="highlighter-rouge">if(typeof process === 'object')</code>. When on app, this would return true. If in browser, false.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript"><span class="k">if</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">typeof</span> <span class="nx">process</span> <span class="o">===</span> <span class="s1">'object'</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">ipcRenderer</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">require</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'electron'</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">ipcRenderer</span>

  <span class="nx">ipcRenderer</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">send</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'listDir'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="s1">'/'</span><span class="p">)</span>

  <span class="nx">ipcRenderer</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">on</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'listDirSuccess'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">event</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">arg</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="c1">// Log the list of files/directories to the console</span>
    <span class="nx">console</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">log</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">arg</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="p">})</span>
<span class="p">}</span> <span class="k">else</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="nx">console</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">log</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'You gotta install our app for this feature'</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="p">}</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>In the above code, if the context is app, you emit <code class="highlighter-rouge">listDir</code> event to the main process and are listening for <code class="highlighter-rouge">listDirSuccess</code> event, which when occurs, you display whatever is being recieved. Simple! Now, let’s listen for the <code class="highlighter-rouge">listDir</code> event in the Main process.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript"><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">ipcMain</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">require</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'electron'</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">ipcMain</span>
<span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">fs</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">require</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'fs'</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="c1">// To read the directory listing</span>

<span class="nx">ipcMain</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">on</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'listDir'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">event</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">arg</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
  <span class="nx">fs</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">readdir</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">arg</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">err</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">files</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="nx">event</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">sender</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">send</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">'listDirSuccess'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">files</span><span class="p">)</span>
  <span class="p">})</span>
<span class="p">})</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>In the application’s index script, listen for <code class="highlighter-rouge">listDir</code> event, which when emitted, read the specific directory in the file system and emit <code class="highlighter-rouge">listDirSuccess</code> event with the array of files/directories.</p>

<p>With ipc module, you could do a lot more when the webpage is accessed from application(electron) context and make use of almost all the system level APIs which Node provides.</p>

<p>Go make the most out of electron. Cheers!</p>]]></description>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dolftax.com//2016/01/renderer-main-communication-in-electron</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>